<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The legend of St. Cuthbert with the antiquities of the Church of Durham / by B.R., Esq.</title>
            <author>Hegge, Robert, 1599-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43253</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15307</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11925646</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11925646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51010</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43253)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51010)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 33:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The legend of St. Cuthbert with the antiquities of the Church of Durham / by B.R., Esq.</title>
                  <author>Hegge, Robert, 1599-1629.</author>
                  <author>R. B. (Richard Baddeley)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 93 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Christopher Eccleston ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by Robert Hegge. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Editor's prologue signed: B.R. [i.e., Richard Baddeley]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cuthbert, --  Saint, Bishop of Lindisfarne, ca. 635-687.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:51010:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>S.<hi rend="sup">t</hi> CUTHBERT</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51010:1"/>
            <p>THE LEGEND OF St. <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THBERT.</hi> WITH THE ANTIQUITIES OF THE <hi>Church</hi> of DURHAM.</p>
            <p>By <hi>B. R.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Chriſtopher Eccleſton</hi> at his ſhop in St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Churchyard, 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:51010:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51010:2"/>
            <head>The PROLOG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough much of the enſuing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be no more conſiſtent with common Reaſon and probability, the the Fables in the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choran,</hi> and ſo cannot have any deſign of engaging the faith of the Reader to the veritie of the relations yet
<pb facs="tcp:51010:3"/>things of this nature giving ſome ſhaddow of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the mind, and being free from any real prejudice to Vertue of Religion men thriftie enough in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of their time, are not ſeldome content to allow ſome waſt hours in reading them, and perhaps with ſome profit and obſervation. At that time when this <hi>Legend</hi> bears date, Miracles were cheap enough, and the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous ignorance of the
<pb facs="tcp:51010:3"/>Vulgar was eaſily abuſed with religious impoſtures. But howſoever ſuch juggles may appear now to the eyes of the more generally know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and undeceived world, I ſhould have charitie enough to believe that the antique invention of them was upon the accompt of promoting the eſteem of Holy Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were not the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on too palpably notorious that they all tended over much to the end of private
<pb facs="tcp:51010:4"/>gain or reputation to the Miracle-mongers; Not that I call in queſtion the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableneſſe of that antient policy how ridiculous ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it appears now; for he was no unwiſe or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> W. Raleigh.</note> man, which ſaid, That <hi>the wiſdom of one age is the fooliſhneſſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who was the Author of this Book, or when by him compiled, or upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, (though probably
<pb facs="tcp:51010:4"/>for his own private diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement) I do ignore in an equal degree, and am not able to give any other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt thereof, then what the Treatiſe it ſelf affords. Had he publiſhed it himſelf (without any improbable conjecture) it had paſſed cenſure with greater ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the <hi>Author</hi> being a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of ſo much ſtile and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage as the Book it ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks him. I am only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in committing it
<pb facs="tcp:51010:5"/>to the Stationer, and guilty of the vanity of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>B. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51010:5"/>
            <head>THE LEGEND OF S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THBERT;</hi> WITH <hi>The</hi> ANTIQUITIES <hi>of the Church of</hi> DURHAM.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ISTORY,</hi> and <hi>PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PHECY</hi> (ſet back to back) make up the true Image of <hi>Janus,</hi> whoſe two faces <hi>Time paſt</hi> and <hi>future</hi> honour as their Overſeers. In <hi>Hiſtory, Time</hi> lives after ſhe is dead; in <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51010:6"/>before ſhe is born. In the one ſhe beholds what ſhe was; in the other, what ſhe will be. But ſith the Theorie of Time to come is the prerogative of a Deity, Man muſt be modeſtly content with this bleſſing beſtowed by <hi>Hiſtory</hi> upon Mortality, that through our Grandfathers eyes we may ſee what hath been. This is all our ſublunary Eternity, if at the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral of things <hi>Hiſtory</hi> become the Epitaph, and reſcue their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries from the grave that entombs their aſhes. And this duty I owe to that Countrey, where I had my Cradle, to renew the decayed Epitaphs upon the Tombſtone of her Antiquities.</p>
            <p>Geographers deal with Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51010:6"/>even as Aſtronomers with their Aſteriſms, and fancy them into ſhapes and reſemblances: ſo that by the liberty of phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <hi>Italy</hi> is compared to a mans legg, <hi>Spaine</hi> to an Oxhide, <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine</hi> to an Hatchet; I may liken the Biſhoprick to the Letter Δ, and <hi>Durham</hi> to a Crab, ſuppoſing the City for the body, and the Suburbs for the clawes. This Countrey lyeth in the boſome of the Ocean, and is embraced in the armes of two chryſtal Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, <hi>Teeſe,</hi> and <hi>Derwen.</hi> The antient Inhabitants in the time of the <hi>Romans,</hi> were the <hi>Brigants;</hi> in the <hi>Heptarchie</hi> of the <hi>Saxons</hi> they were called <hi>Deiri:</hi> for the honour of which Province, the Children
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51010:7"/>thereof in the time of <hi>Aella</hi> being to be ſold at <hi>Rome,</hi> gave occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the replanting of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, by <hi>Anguſtine</hi> the Engliſh Apoſtle, ſent hither by Pope <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictus,</hi> at the entreaty of <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> then Archdeacon of <hi>Rome:</hi> who facetely alluding to the names of their Nation, Province, and King, concluded <hi>ut Angli An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis ſimiles de irâ Dei eruerentur, &amp; Allelujah cantare docerentur.</hi> The firſt of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Kings (who made conqueſt as well of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion as Men) that in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince was dipt in the ſacred La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Baptiſm, was the renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Oſwald, Qui Genti ſuae primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tias ſanctitatis dederit;</hi> and is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be the firſt of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51010:7"/>Race, that was illuſtrious by miracles. This Prince ſent once for a learned Monk out of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (<hi>Aidanus</hi> by name) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert his Subjects from Paganiſm, and ſeated him in the Epiſcopal Chair of <hi>Lindisferne, Anno Dom.</hi> 635. where while the Biſhop taught in the <hi>Scotiſh</hi> tongue, the King underſtanding both langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, ſtood and interpreted his Sermons in <hi>Engliſh.</hi> This great Monarch, that great and pious Founder of the Church (to whoſe womb all the Churches in the <hi>North</hi> owe their birth) in a battel with a Pagan Prince loſt his life and the day. But with this advantage (whiles <hi>Penda</hi> left him not a head to wear a Crown
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51010:8"/>withall) he received a more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Diadem of Martyrdom; And as fury perſecuting revenge after death tore his body in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo the devotion of Time diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed the reliques to ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<q>
                  <l>—Nempe jacere</l>
                  <l>Uno non potuit tanta ruina loco.</l>
               </q> For whoſe ſepulchre there was as great contention amongſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Churches, as in old time amongſt the <hi>Graecians</hi> for the Cradle of <hi>Homer.</hi> His Corps were brought to <hi>Lindisfern,</hi> and from thence tranſlated with St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his body to <hi>Durham</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey. His Arm was preſerved in a Silver Casket at <hi>Bedburga,</hi> or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51010:8"/>
               <hi>Bambrough,</hi> not far ſeated from the <hi>Holy Iſland,</hi> and at that time the great Metropolis of thoſe parts. This ſacred Relique re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the bleſſing of <hi>Aidanus,</hi> and was honored as a Monument of incorruption. An Hiſtory which to this effect by <hi>Beda</hi> is related, That upon an <hi>Eaſter day</hi> as the King ſate at dinner, his ſervants told him that there was poor folk that expected alms at his gate; who forthwith bid him both carry them meat, and diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the platter (which was of ſilver) among them; with which fact of charity <hi>Aidanus</hi> (who ſate by him) much delighted, took him by the right arm, with this hearty wiſh, <hi>Never let this arm
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51010:9"/>periſh!</hi> This glorious Martyrs death was the end of <hi>Aidanus</hi> life, and the Pagans at one blow kill'd a Prince, and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, who thought it a ſin to live, after ſo good a King was dead: the Soul of which Biſhop St <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> happened to ſee (in the dead of the night) carried up with great melodie by a Quire of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels into Heaven: which viſion ſo ſeized upon his affection, that reſolving upon an holier courſe of life, he betook himſelf to the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery of <hi>Mailros,</hi> built by <hi>Aida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> by the bank of <hi>Tweede,</hi> and in his journey thither ſhewed a great ſpecimen of his humility, devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and gratitude; for being ſeized upon both by night, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51010:9"/>hunger, he was forced to enter into an empty cottage, where he found no other hoſt for enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment than a horſe, who eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and turning up the hay, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered part of a loaf, which ſome Shepherd had hid; at which the Saint right glad, ſaid Grace, and thankfully giving the horſe one half, ſatisfied himſelf with the other, and lodging there all night, the next day came to <hi>Mailros;</hi> where he no ſooner entred, but <hi>Boyſilous</hi> Prior of the ſame Abbey (as if he had read in his Forehead a Prophetical Phyſiognomie of his future Sanctity) ran, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him in his armes, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented him to <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ta</hi> the Abbot,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51010:10"/>who committed him to <hi>Boyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous</hi> for his Tutor, with whom I leave him, teaching him St. <hi>Johns</hi> Goſpel; which book in honour of the Scholar, was kept in <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in Prior <hi>Turgots</hi> time, called <hi>Codex Sancti Cuthberti:</hi> on which, after ſo many Centuries of years, no Moth ever durſt preſume to feed.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Lindisferne</hi> by the royal Charter of <hi>Oſwald,</hi> became the Mother Church, and Nurſery of Religion amongſt the <hi>Bernicians</hi> under <hi>Aidanus,</hi> from whom the Epiſcopal race of the Prelates of <hi>Durham</hi> reckon their ſucceſſion. In antient deſcription it was an Iſland but twice a day, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by <hi>Neptune</hi> only at full
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51010:10"/>tide, and at Ebbe ſhaked hands with the Continent: (for ſo I may call the voluminous Iſle of <hi>Great Britaine,</hi> in proportion of this littel Iſle, which in a Monk of <hi>Durhams</hi> Topographie was in compaſſe 8. miles.)</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Holy Iſland,</hi> (ſo Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for St. <hi>Cuthberts</hi> ſanctity) ſtood the renowned Monaſtery founded by King <hi>Oſwald,</hi> where <hi>Finanus, Aidanus</hi> his ſucceſſor, built a Cathedral of wood that<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with reeds, which reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth thoſe times, when</p>
            <q>
               <l>Jupiter anguſtâ vix totus ſtabat in aede,</l>
               <l>Inque Jovis dextrâ fictile fulmen e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at.</l>
               <l>Frondibus ornabant quae jam Capitolia gem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis,</l>
               <l>Paſcebat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuas ipſe ſenator oves.</l>
            </q>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51010:11"/>
            <p> But is was not long, till <hi>Ead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his ſucceſſor, inſtead of this conſecrated thatch, apparreld over the whole Church with a robe of Lead; a work of devotion and coſt; though it is not the Maſon, but the Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per that makes a Church.</p>
            <p>In this <hi>Iſland</hi> 14. Biſhops ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively aſcended the Epiſcopal ſeat, among whom St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> was accounted as a glorious Star of the firſt magnitude in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent of the Church; who when he had lived a Monaſterial life 15 years in the Abby of <hi>Mail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros,</hi> was preferred by <hi>Eata</hi> to the Priory of <hi>Lindisferne,</hi> which dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity he bare 12 years in ſuch ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity of life, that the Devil (as I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51010:11"/>cannot blame him) was much grieved at his Vertues; who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Cheats (with which the Monks make the Devil a fool) in a certain village, as the Saint was preaching, ſet an houſe on fire, to draw the people from his Sermon: which, when the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey folk marvelled they could not quench, it was diſcovered to St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> to be phantaſtical fire, and the Devils deluſion. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 12 years, (as before) he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned up his Priorſhip, to become an Hermit, chooſing the Iſland <hi>Ferne,</hi> ſeated in the main Ocean, for the place of his Hermitage, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 676. This Iſle, as void of men, as full of Devils, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the ſcene or ſtage whereon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51010:12"/>Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> acted all his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; for at his arrival, the <hi>Spirits</hi> that had frequented this <hi>Iſle,</hi> were glad to fly, and forego their title. The Rocks poured out their water, and the Earth, (as if there had been a return of the Golden Age) brought forth Corne without Tillage. And here he conſecrated 9 years to Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, ſo wholly devoted to Heaven, that he forgot he was on Earth, and in a whole year to put off his ſhoes. And although he wanted Men for his Auditors, yet he ceaſed not to preach to the Birds, that eat up his Corn, who ſo confuted them out of this text, <hi>Non aliena concupiſces,</hi> that they would never after eat his barley.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51010:12"/>In like manner he reclaimed two Crows from ſtealing, and rapine, that pluckt off his thatch from his Anchorage to build their neſt, and made them ſo penitent, that they lay at his feet proſtrate for abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the next day brought him a piece of Pork to make him ſatisfaction, with many more Wonders, if they might be related upon the credit of a <hi>Legend.</hi> But here is enough to ſhew what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the Monks took of that Ages Devotion, whoſe practices were to deviſe Miracles of their <hi>Saint,</hi> which (as Superſtition is alwayes credulous) were as eaſily believed. Thus, to gain a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend opinion from the Pagans of Chriſtianity, to cozen the people
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51010:13"/>with Legends of wonders, who while they defended Truth with Falſhood, and their Impoſtures diſcovered to wiſer Ages, have made Religion rather ſuſpected, than any way advanced it; for Truth never needed the protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Forgery, but will carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Victory without Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie. But Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> recalls my digreſſion to his Iſle, where he had ſo many combats with the Devil, that (if you will borrow an Optick Glaſſe from Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) you may ſee the print of his feet in many places there, till this day. It any landed at his Iſland to ſee him in devotion, he ran into his Hermitage, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed out of his window: only
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51010:13"/>in love he bare to the Abbateſſe of <hi>Collingham,</hi> at great entreaty he ſayled into <hi>Cocket</hi> Iſle to her; where every night (as his cuſtom was) going down to the ſhore to pray, two Sea-monſters came kneeling to him, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him: who when they had received their bleſſing, returned to the deep, and he again to his Anchorage, where whiles he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned himſelf, and lived more obſcured in his Cell, the more illuſtrious was his fame abroad; and in a Synod at <hi>Twiford</hi> upon <hi>Slu,</hi> in the preſence of King <hi>Egfrid,</hi> he was choſen Biſhop. This dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity was propheſied unto him, when he was a boy, by an Infant of 3, years old, who gravely told
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51010:14"/>told him, <hi>It becomed not a Biſhop to play with children.</hi> But Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> had ſo wedded his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to a ſolitary life, that neither letters, nor Embaſſadors from the Synod, could either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, or perſwade him to take upon him the government of the Church; till the King himſelf, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the Lords of the Nobility, ſail'd to this Iſle, and with the ſame company might have beſieged, and taken a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whiles he was conquering St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi>'s reſolution. Thus (though the caſe be now altered) honour purſued him, that fled from her, and preferment found him out, that hid himſelf from it. The Biſhoprick of <hi>Hexam</hi> was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51010:14"/>then void, to which <hi>Eata</hi> remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, gave place to St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> to be inſtalled in <hi>Lindisferne.</hi> King <hi>Egfrid</hi> alſo to enlarge his Dioceſſe, gave him a great part of the City of <hi>Yorke,</hi> and alſo the City of <hi>Luell,</hi> with 5. miles circuit about it, where Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> built a Nunnery, beſides other Royal Donations, as the Abbey of <hi>Mailros,</hi> and <hi>Rippon;</hi> But St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his minde was alway on his anchorage, whither he ſhortly betook himſelf, and in his Cell ended his life, and began his miracles, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 687. But if I were to make his Funeral Oration, 1 would not inſert a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his praiſes that he was an Anchoret; for thus to unman
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51010:15"/>himſelf, to contemplate himſelf into a Deity, argued more pride, than Religion. 'Tis true, that an Hermit is either a god, or a beaſt; yet ſith man is more ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical with the one, than the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it is eaſie to ſuſpect, which way the Metamorphoſis will tend; For if you would have the lively picture of an Hermit truly repreſented, look upon <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> in his curſe, when he was driven from men, and did eat graſſe as the Oxen, when his body was wet with the dew of Heaven, till his hairs became as Eagles feathers, and his nails as the clawes of birds. Thus therefore for an Hermit to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate himſelf from being
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51010:15"/>a holy Citizen of the World, what is it elſe but to ſin againſt the Common weal and definition of a man, to whom ſociety is as natural as to be a Creature: ſo that whiles others think it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion in him, I ſhall rather think it a melancholy diſtemper.</p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> laſt Will and Teſtament directed to the <hi>Monks,</hi> was, to bury him at the Eaſt ſide of his Oratory, in a Coffin that the Venerable <hi>Tuda</hi> gave him, and for to wrap, or winde his Corps in the ſheet that <hi>Ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a</hi> Abbateſſe of <hi>Tinmouth</hi> once ſent him for a token, which for the reverence of that Holy woman he had never worn in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time. And laſtly, if they ſhould
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51010:16"/>be invaded by Pagans, to carry his bones away with them. Thus Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> Sainted himſelt in his life-time, and gave them no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, what a precious Relique he ſhould be, when he was dead. All theſe Petition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were duely performed; only at the requeſt of the Monks, he permitted that his body ſhould be tranſported to <hi>Lindisferne;</hi> where, in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, at the right ſide of the High Altar he was ſolemnly layd in a Tomb of Stone. Now were the times when the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Miracles</hi> begun to build Cburches, and Religious Houſes ſo to ſwarm, and multiply, that all <hi>England</hi> ſeemed but one great Monaſtery, and called by the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51010:16"/>Pope, <hi>Terra Sacerdotum.</hi> But <hi>Time</hi> (that hath the Sublunary World for her continual ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet) hath ſo fed upon theſe <hi>antient buildings,</hi> that ſome ſhe quite devoured, others pick'd to the bone, and what ſhe hath left for ſtanding diſhes, <hi>Hoſtility</hi> hath quite eaten up and defaced: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that great <hi>Climacterical year,</hi> when <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th durſt incur thoſe thundering <hi>Anathemata's,</hi> which (by the appointment of the <hi>Monks</hi>) attended the violation of Abbey-lands,
<q>
                  <l>Si de tot laeſis ſua numina quiſque deorum</l>
                  <l>Vindicet in poenas, non ſat is unuserit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>But I moſt bewail thoſe Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51010:17"/>whoſe Names are buried in their aſhes, and their very ruines ſuffer the death of a Sepulcher, and dye twice, becauſe they want a Monument that they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Of theſe Monuments of <hi>Devotion,</hi> that live the life of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, and belonged once to St. <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> ſtood <hi>Collingham;</hi> This Monaſtery conſiſted of <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Nuns,</hi> over whom <hi>Ebba</hi> was ſome times Abbateſſe, who received her veyle of <hi>Finanus</hi> the ſecond Biſhop of the <hi>Holy Iſland.</hi> Among the <hi>Bernicians</hi> likewiſe was the Epiſcopal ſeat of <hi>Hagustaldum,</hi> or <hi>Hexam,</hi> beſtowed by King <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred</hi> upon Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> which <hi>Malmesbury</hi> (ſomewhat miſtaken in the Scale of Miles) placed but
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51010:17"/>50 miles from <hi>Yorke,</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth (for beauty of ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) before any building on this ſide the <hi>Alpes.</hi> In this Church ſate 9 <hi>Biſhops,</hi> among whom the learned <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Bever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> (not to be named by an <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> man without a preface of honour) was advanced to that dignity by <hi>King Alfred,</hi> and then ſwayed the Paſtoral Staff, till he was tranſlated to <hi>Yorke.</hi> In his younger yeares he was brought up (according to the nobility of his birth) under <hi>Hilda</hi> Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bateſſe of <hi>Strenſhall,</hi> or <hi>Whitby</hi> in <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> of which ſhee was alſo Foundreſſe. Afterward he was Scholar to the <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Theodore</hi> of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51010:18"/>born at <hi>Tarſus</hi> is <hi>Cilicia,</hi> was the firſt that brought <hi>Learning</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> as well as Religion; who bringing over with him <hi>Homer,</hi> (the firſt we read of in this <hi>Iſle</hi>) and other good <hi>Authors,</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted many Famous Scholars in the <hi>Greek Tongue,</hi> and <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> where among the reſt I find Saint <hi>Beda, Herebald, Whilfride,</hi> and this <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Beverley;</hi> who at the tranſlation of the School of <hi>Creke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lade</hi> (which <hi>Theodore</hi> had there planted) to <hi>Oxford,</hi> was the firſt <hi>Maſter of Art</hi> in that <hi>Vniverſity,</hi> as it appreareth out of an antient Window in <hi>Salisbury Library</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Beverleyes</hi> Picture: And he that goeth higher to fetch the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> than from
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51010:18"/>his time, doth but grope in the dark. This age of 800 years is enough to prove <hi>Cambridge</hi> the <hi>younger Sister,</hi> till <hi>Lelands</hi> deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will follow, that <hi>Sigebert</hi> King of the <hi>East Angles</hi> founded that <hi>Vniverſity;</hi> becauſe <hi>Bede,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him <hi>Malmsbury</hi> relate that he erected divers <hi>Schools</hi> in this Kingdom; but in neither Author, <hi>Grant</hi> or <hi>Cambridge</hi> is mentioned, nor in any <hi>Writer</hi> ſince for 400. years after, to be an <hi>Vniverſity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return with pardon to Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> who had now lyen Eleven years in his <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> when the <hi>Monks</hi> thought by this time to take his bones diſrob'd of fleſh, and put them among other <hi>reliques;</hi> But whiles they opened
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51010:19"/>his Coffin, they ſtart at a <hi>wonder;</hi> they look'd for bones and found fleſh; they expected a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſaw an entire body, with joynts flexible, and his face ſo diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling Death, that elſe where it is true that Sleep is the image of Death, here Death was the image of Sleep; nay his funeral weeds were ſo freſh, as if <hi>putrefaction</hi> had not dared to take him by the Coat. This was rather to pay his debt to <hi>Heaven,</hi> than to <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that after he ſhould reſtore his <hi>ſoul</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> he ſhould keep back the <hi>payment</hi> of his <hi>body</hi> from <hi>corruption.</hi> This <hi>Miracle</hi> of <hi>incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption Bede</hi> reports, who was eleven years old at Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his death, in relating whereof he
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51010:19"/>made no <hi>Lye,</hi> but told <hi>one,</hi> the <hi>History</hi> of whoſe <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> he writ, and took upon truſt from the information of the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Lindisfern,</hi> who had deflowred all the <hi>miracles</hi> of <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> and beſtowed them upon their Saint <hi>Cuthbert:</hi> ſo barren brain'd Monks were they, that would not invent new ones, but ſuch as were writ before to their hands; for <hi>Adam</hi> could not be commander of the creatures in the ſtate of innocency, but St. <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> alſo muſt have the ſavage beaſts to do him homage. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> could not entertain three Angels under on Oak, but Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> muſt have Angels for his gueſts as the Monaſtery of <hi>Rippon.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:51010:20"/>The Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> could not eat <hi>Manna,</hi> and <hi>Angels food,</hi> but Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> muſt have three <hi>Loaves</hi> beſtowed upon him by an <hi>Angel,</hi> which were baked in <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi> A <hi>Raven</hi> could not bring <hi>Elias</hi> fleſh, but an <hi>Eagle</hi> muſt bring Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> fiſh. And here alſo this <hi>miracle</hi> hath an <hi>Idea</hi> in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> that when his Mother ſail'd with him from <hi>Ireland</hi> into <hi>Scotland,</hi> the books of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> fell into the ſea, which forthwith was ſwallowed up of a <hi>Sea calf,</hi> and delivered to them at their land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Take but the <hi>Pſaltes</hi> for a <hi>man,</hi> and the <hi>Sea calf</hi> for a <hi>whale,</hi> and here you have the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>Jonas,</hi> with many ſuch Hiſtories of wonders, with which the <hi>Monks</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51010:20"/>delighted the ſuperſtition of the times. This illuſtrious miracle of Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> body <hi>incorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible</hi> after <hi>death,</hi> raiſed the Church to that height of renown, that King <hi>Celwolphus</hi> in opinion of his <hi>ſanctity,</hi> forſook his <hi>Royalty</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>Monk</hi> in <hi>Lindisferne,</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him ſuch Kingly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and donations of Lands, that he ſeemed rather to reſign his <hi>Kingdom</hi> to the <hi>Church,</hi> than to his <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> and became a <hi>Monk,</hi> to make St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing upon him <hi>Warkeworth</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Heycliffe, Billingham, Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſtre, Huttingham, Edulingham, Elingham;</hi> Towns that (for ought I know) have either out-lived their names, or names that have
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51010:21"/>ſurvived their Towns. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, he was a welcome man to their <hi>Monaſtery,</hi> that for his ſake it was granted the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Lindisferne</hi> of drink wine, who were before to drink water, thought they that drank after St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in his Cup, found ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times water turn'd to wine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Miracle. This devout Prince, after he had divers years worn a <hi>Monks Coole,</hi> was intomb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Norham,</hi> which Town <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulphus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a Caſtle.</p>
            <p>After this <hi>Miracle of incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Eadfrid</hi> The Biſhop cauſed him to be laid in a new <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> and to be placed in more ſtate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, about the pavement of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51010:21"/>the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> for it was not fit, that he ſhould have his grave among the dead, whoſe body ſeemed to live without a ſoul, and with a ſleep to cheate mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taliſy of a death.</p>
            <p>By this time the very ground that S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cuthbert</hi> had trod on was accounted holy, who made eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place he frequented a Church. <hi>Eadfrid</hi> in Honour of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence built up his Hermitage, where (as if after S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cuthbert</hi> a genius of <hi>Sanctity</hi> had frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that place) <hi>Etheldred</hi> a <hi>Monk</hi> of <hi>Rippon</hi> lived an Hermit 12 years.</p>
            <p>Thus for a long time flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>Monks</hi> of this Church, till the <hi>Danes</hi> diſturbed their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51010:22"/>proſperity, who now begun to make incurſions upon the frontiers of this land, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their piracies, and invaſions, till they had made a compleate conqueſt in King <hi>Harold,</hi> which Monarchy ſhortly after yeilded to the <hi>Norman</hi> victory, and <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> twice Conquered in ſeventy years. Theſe were the times when ſo many Monaſteries (which the Devotion of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages had erected) had their Funerals, and Entombed themſelves in their own aſhes; Then periſhed that famous <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porium</hi> of <hi>Hartlepoale,</hi> where the Religious <hi>Jew</hi> built a <hi>Nunry,</hi> of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> own I may ſay as <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:51010:22"/>
               <q>Quammagnifueris integra, fracta doces.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The ruines ſhew how great ſhe was in her Glory, but now remaines to paſſengers as a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of Devotion, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility; Then were demoliſhed the two Monaſteries of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul at Wormouth,</hi> and <hi>Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> built by two Abbots, <hi>Celfr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> and <hi>Benedict.</hi> Thoſe two Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties mutual fraternity had ſo ſirmely united, that they ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but one Monaſtery in two places, and ſhall ever be famous, while the memory of Venerable <hi>Bede</hi> ſhall be honoured of the learned: for (in thoſe times) in the ſame Monaſteries he had
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51010:23"/>his firſt education under <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict</hi> a Reverent Abbot, and one whom Antiquity defraudes not of thoſe due praiſes, that he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured choiſe bookes from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea for his Monaſtery: and was the firſt that brought into <hi>England</hi> the uſe of Glaſs win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows into Churches. In his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per years he was brought up by <hi>Theodore,</hi> under whom he was inſtructed both in ſacred and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular learning, and attained to that maturity of judgment, that never writer ſince hath brought greater honour to his Nation: whiles he confined himſelf to his Cel, his fame travalled to <hi>Rome,</hi> where Pope <hi>Sergius,</hi> in a letter to <hi>Celfrid</hi> the Abbot, earneſtly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51010:23"/>intreated him to come in perſon: but for ought I know, without accepting the Popes curteſie, he dyed in his Monaſtery, which in memory of his preſence, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it had lain waſt by the Pagans 208. years, was re-edified by <hi>Adwin</hi> a <hi>Monk</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fury of the <hi>Danes</hi> ſtill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing continued by the Sea coaſt to <hi>Tinmouth,</hi> where <hi>Herca</hi> of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his acquaintance had been Abbateſs: ſo that it was high time for the <hi>Monks</hi> to look about them; for they begun to-underſtand by the overthrow of their neighbouring Abbeyes, that it was in vaine to think that the <hi>Danes</hi> would (like the Divel) be affrighted away with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51010:24"/>Holy water, and ſaw by the bad ſucceſs of Monaſteries, that it was not ſafe truſting the protection of a Saint, and ſo concluded (according to St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his will) upon flight: and putting all their reliques in Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his Coffins, left the Pagans the ſpoile of an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Church, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 893. now it was <hi>Eardulphus</hi> his fortune to be Biſhop in thoſe trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome times, who with his whole Clergy of people fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> body, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by ſeven <hi>Monkes</hi> (as <abbr>Eſq</abbr> of his body) beſides whom none might preſume to touch his Coffin under the danger of <hi>Vzzahs</hi> puniſhment. Theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51010:24"/>had been enough to have unſainted Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> when purſued both by foes, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken by an homebred enemie, famine that would afford him no releif. They were now driven to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſea, and might well complaine with the old <hi>Brittains</hi> to <hi>Boetius</hi> the Conſul, <hi>Repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt nos Barbari ad mare; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellit nos mare ad Barbaros, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter haec oriuntur duo genera fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, aut jugulamur, out in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgimur</hi> Not far had they ſailed from the ſhoare, when both the Sea and the winds were up in armes, and both agianſt their Pinnace, which both <hi>Aeolus</hi> and <hi>Naptune</hi> might have worſhipped for her ſacred carriage of a Biſhop, and his
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51010:25"/>Clergy, with ſo many reliques, that it ſeemed rather a Cathedral then a ſhip: but the Sea had not that Religion to hear their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, threatning them ſo near with ſhipwrack, that they had not that confidence in their Saint to encourage the Mariners with <hi>Ne metuas, Cuthbertum vehis,</hi> who now himſelf wanted ſome other Saint to invocate for help, and was in danger to be drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, after he was dead. Where had then been the Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> and the devotion of Kings to his <hi>Sepulchre?</hi> Where had then been the <hi>tutelary Deity</hi> againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> and the lands of the Church, called Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his Patrimonie? How then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51010:25"/>ſhould Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his <hi>Hally. marke-folke</hi> be free from Tribute, and ſervice in War; and the fat <hi>Monks</hi> fed ſo many years, with eaſe, and plenty; if now their Saint had been entombed in the ſea, andhad erected his Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal ſeat amongſt the fiſhes? This <hi>Sacrilegious storme</hi> ſtruck the ſhip with ſuch a <hi>palſie,</hi> that it ſhakt out the <hi>Text</hi> of the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Sea:</hi> This Book in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of Saint <hi>Cuthbert, Eadfrid</hi> had writ with his own hands, and <hi>Bilfrid</hi> the Anchorite had cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly painted; in which art of drawing the <hi>Monks</hi> were admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble expert, who with ſuch pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures knew bow they enhaunted vulgar eyes. The art, I confeſs,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51010:26"/>is both ingenuous, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable; only it argues, that the <hi>Monks</hi> were at great leiſure. Thus whether the <hi>Sea</hi> envying the land ſuch a precious Jewel as Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> was, ſtrove to have it her ſelf; or whether he himſelf raiſed the tempeſt, to ſhew that their attempt for <hi>Jreland</hi> was againſt his mind, forthwith both the <hi>Sea,</hi> and the winds conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and brought them to the ſhore, where was great joy at their arrival, much ſorrow for their Book being drowned; till <hi>Hundred,</hi> one of the ſeven ſquires of his body, was bid by Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in his ſleep to go ſeek on the ſhore at <hi>Whiterne</hi> where he found it in its former ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51010:26"/>without the blemiſh of a letter. If this be true, then ſure I am, this Book had better fortune in the <hi>Sea,</hi> than the Bookes of Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> have now in his Library at <hi>Durham,</hi> which once was a litle <hi>Vatican</hi> of choiſe manuſcripts, but now ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, than a library: rather a place of a <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> than a place to conſerve bookes; for ſince the art of Printing was invented, whereby men after a more cheap way could attaine to ſome ſuperficial Learning; old manuſcripts were bequeathed to the <hi>Mothes:</hi> and <hi>Pigeons,</hi> and <hi>Jack-dawes</hi> became the only ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in Church libraries: and bookes were wounded with pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knifes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51010:27"/>for their pictures, with as great cruelty, as <hi>Caſſia,</hi> or <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Scotus</hi> martyrd by their own Schollers.</p>
            <p>But to return, <hi>Hundredus</hi> had alſo in a night an Oracle from Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> that he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to a Tree, on which he ſhould find a dun Horſe profer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſervice to draw the Waine, whereon they ſhould lay Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his Coffin. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of this Horſe (as guided by Saint. <hi>Cuthbert</hi>) they followed, whitherſoever he went, and at length by the providence of the Horſe, or Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> they came to <hi>Creca,</hi> where (for 4. Months) they were kindly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by the Abbot, and had
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51010:27"/>leiſure to tell ſtories of their travailes' And here again Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> plaid the Pope, and in a viſion ſent <hi>Eadred</hi> Abbot of <hi>Luel,</hi> upon and Embaſſage to the Camp of the <hi>Danes,</hi> that they ſhould Crown <hi>Guthred</hi> King; But what authority Saint <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> had to nominate a King, or what reaſon the Army had to believe a dream, muſt be ranked among his <hi>Miracles.</hi> Now for <hi>Guthred</hi> to be made a King, what is it elſe but to be Saint <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> ſubject, and to oblige his <hi>Royalty</hi> to thoſe <hi>Monks</hi> that as impudently incroacht upon ſo fair an <hi>advantage?</hi> For firſt they obtain the Reſtauration of the Epiſcopal <hi>See</hi> in <hi>Cuncaceſtle</hi> on
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51010:28"/>the ſtreet of <hi>Eardulphus,</hi> where he aſcended the Poncificial chaire, under the protection of this new <hi>King,</hi> to whom (once more) the aforeſaid Abbot muſt bring a meſſage from Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in a dream to bid him give all the lands between <hi>Weer</hi> and <hi>Tyne</hi> for ever to his Church; or elſe the <hi>Monks</hi> would be ready to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braide him with ingratitude: Thus was the poor <hi>Prince</hi> robd of all his Kingdoms, and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſet on Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his head. They pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded alſo further to demand the freedom of a <hi>ſanctuary</hi> for St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his Church; that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhould commit any crime, might fly to this <hi>Sepulchre,</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51010:28"/>have 37. dayes reſcue: that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther magiſtrates, nor Juſtice might curbe the freedom of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, either againſt Heaven or ſtate; for no other uſe was commonly made of aſylus's, then that men might ſin more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and diſloyally appeal from the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Lawes</hi> to the protection of a <hi>Saint.</hi> Thus was the <hi>King</hi> cheated of his <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty</hi> by the <hi>Monks,</hi> who had now got the art of enſlaving the devotion of <hi>Kings</hi> to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and falſe purpoſes. At this time alſo the great <hi>Alfredus</hi> ſwore fealty to St <hi>Cuthbert</hi> and his Clergy by whoſe help he was perſwaded he had got the victory over the Pagans, and not only confirmed to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51010:29"/>them by his Royal Charter what <hi>Guthred</hi> had given them, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo freed the Inhabitants in the land of Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> from tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and ſervice in War, with fearfull <hi>Anathemata</hi>'s to any of his ſucceſſors, who durſt infringe any of the ſaid liberties. What elſe was this, than for a <hi>King</hi> to deprive himſelf of that ſervice, which even by the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is due to a <hi>Prince</hi> from a ſubject? In what eſteem this St. was to King <hi>Alfred,</hi> I gather from the conſecration of the Chappel to Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in the Univerſity Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> in which Colledge I have ſeen King <hi>Alfrid</hi> and Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> painted together; the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51010:29"/>King thus beſpeaking the Saint in a <hi>Pentameter:</hi>
               <q>Hic in honore tui Collegium ſtatui.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> thus replying in an <hi>Hexameter,</hi>
               <q>Quod ſtatuiſti in eo, pervertentes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledico.</q>
            </p>
            <p>But I obſerve that Saint <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> was either an angry Saint, or the <hi>Monks</hi> uſed to curſe in his name, as appears by a Diſtick in <hi>Trinity Colledge</hi> ingraven in a Wooden beame, built for a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of <hi>Monks,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham: Anno Domini</hi> 1343.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:51010:30"/>
            <q>
               <l>Terras <hi>Cuthberti</hi> qui non ſpoliare ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur,</l>
               <l>Eſſe queant certi, quod morte mala mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But to return, King <hi>Alfreds</hi> devotion to Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> whom he made to ſhare with him in his <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and honoured his name under his own coyne, as it is proved by the true portrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of ſome ſilver Money dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged up <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1611. in little <hi>Crosby</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> and ſent to the Learned <hi>Antiquary,</hi> and my honoured friend Mr. <hi>Thomas Allen</hi> of <hi>Glocester</hi> Hall in <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus after the aged <hi>Eardul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:51010:30"/>(the laſt Biſhop of <hi>Lindis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferne,</hi> and firſt of <hi>Chester</hi>) had ſhared with Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in proſperity and adverſity, and had ſeen the flouriſhing eſtate of this new Church (ſprung up like a <hi>Phoenix</hi> out of the aſhes of the former) full of days, and honour yielded to nature, and was entombed at <hi>Chester Anno Domini</hi> 894. in which year alſo dyed the victorious <hi>Alfred,</hi> who on his Death-bed bequeathed the love he bare to Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> as a pretious legacy to his ſon <hi>Edward:</hi> chargeing him to be an Heir as well to his Devotion, as to his Kingdomes: King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> alſo zealous in propagation of Piety (as if it had been <hi>ex
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51010:31"/>traduce</hi> to theſe Princes to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi>) left his ſon <hi>Athelſtan</hi> executor of his love to that Church. In this high and mighty Prince, the heptarchy compleatly expired, who was the firſt abſolute Monarch of this land, after the <hi>Saxon</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, which was great joy to St. <hi>Cuthberts</hi> Monks, that they had ſo great countenance of a King that was as willing as able to protect them; of whom they gave this report, that never any King ſo dearly loved Saint <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> or beſtowed upon his Church more Princely Donations than <hi>Athelstan,</hi> whom the <hi>Monks</hi> had brought to that obedience of miſſeemely Devotion, that he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51010:31"/>came in Pilgrimage to St. <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> ſhrine barefoot. How could not the <hi>Monks</hi> but (like Magicians, when they meet) laugh one at another to ſee Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty ſo captivated under ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and Majeſty ſo deject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when the end of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Sanctities</hi> was only ſloth, and fatneſſe. This devout Prince leading an army into <hi>Scotland</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted aſide to Saint <hi>Cutberts</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, imploring his aide, and patronage in his Wars, and with many princely gifts bought the good wiſhes of the Monks in his journey. The ſouldiers alſo offer, at the Kings command, 96. pounds, when it had been more ſit, that Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> out of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51010:32"/>his Church-treaſure ſhould have beſtowed as much on them, who with their ſword and blood ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the victory: yet Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> and the benedictions of his idle Monks muſt have the glory of the conqueſt; which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion made King <hi>Ethelſtans</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a like occaſion into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> take Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in his way, honouring the Sepulchre with many kingly offerings, and renewing to them the Charters of his predeceſſours. And here I will not deny, but as it may be expedient for the Common Wealth by way of policy, that ſome men (though altogether guiltleſſe of that art) be thought by the vulgar people skilfull Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51010:32"/>or Conjurers, that they who will rather truſt God with their unlawful ſecrets then man, might be more affraid to offend, leſt they ſhould be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed: So the King might make good uſe of that opinion of Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> being a tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary <hi>Deity</hi> againſt the <hi>Scots;</hi> In conceite of whoſe <hi>protection,</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely the <hi>Engliſh Souldiers</hi> were much <hi>encouraged,</hi> and <hi>animated</hi> to the great diſadvantage of their <hi>enemies,</hi> and obtaining the <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> As alſo this perſwaſion kept this part from frequent <hi>incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> when the <hi>Monks</hi> had inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo many fearful miracles that befell thoſe that attempted either by <hi>Hoſtility</hi> or <hi>stealth</hi> to wrong
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51010:33"/>any thing belonging to the Saint. But I wonder, how the <hi>Monks</hi> could maintain this Impoſture ſo many years, when men growing wiſer begun to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the falſehood of the <hi>Monks,</hi> as deviſers of miracles for their own gain: and it ſeems the <hi>Monks</hi> were put to a great ſhift to maintaine the Saint-ſhips of Saint <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> and Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> when they pretended ſuch amity between them, that they that belonged to Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> muſt be made whole by Saint <hi>Becket:</hi> a ſmall jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for a ſick man to travaile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Canterbury</hi> and <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> But the <hi>Monks</hi> knew full well, that ſome would not be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51010:33"/>able to undertake the <hi>Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi> others rather to uſe the Saint-ſhip of a <hi>Phyſician;</hi> ſome again to be content rather to dye at home, others to recover in the way; laſtly ſome, either to dye in their jorney, or elſe to ſave the credit of their Saint, that they ſhould never come thither.</p>
            <p>But to return to the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> who with their Biſhop enjoyed ſuch calme of Eaſe, that they make no noiſe in Hiſtory, till the rumor of the landing of <hi>Danes</hi> troubled their reſt; This was the 115. year after they had ſeated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in <hi>Chester;</hi> when <hi>Ald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winus</hi> then Biſhop was bid by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51010:34"/>Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in his ſleep to avoid the fury of the <hi>Danes.</hi> But after ſix Moneths, and peace concluded, in their return from thence, there happened a weighty miracle: for at <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denlaw</hi> Eaſt from <hi>Durham,</hi> Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his Coffin was ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, that all the company that accompanied his corps, could not draw the waine whereon they lay; by which they perceived ſo much of Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his mind, that he would not be carried to <hi>Cheſter.</hi> At length after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of three days faſt, it was revealed to <hi>Eadmarus</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout <hi>Monk,</hi> that <hi>Dunholme</hi> was the place of his perpetual reſt: and then two or three could
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51010:34"/>draw the cart, which before the whole <hi>Dioceſſe</hi> of people could not ſo much as move. Now concerning the vulgar fable of the duu Cow and the Milk maid, that directed them to <hi>Dunholme,</hi> I find nothing in the Hiſtorians of this Church who would not leave out any thing that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> by way of a miracle. The <hi>Topography</hi> of <hi>Dunholme</hi> was at that time more beholden to nature for fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then fertility, where thick Woods, both hindered the ſtars from viewing the earth, and the earth from proſpect of Heaven. Here the <hi>Monks</hi> with extempory devotion made with boughs and branches of trees
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51010:35"/>rather an arbour than a Church to place Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in: but from this Chappel of boughs they tranſlated him to another Church, <hi>Whitekerke,</hi> where he reſted in eaſe. <hi>Aldwinus</hi> the Biſhop raiſed up no ſmal build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſtone work for his Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral Church; where all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple between <hi>Coqued</hi> and <hi>Teaſe</hi> were at work three years, and were paid for their pains with expectation of treaſure in heaven; a very cheap way to pay work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for their wages! Into this new <hi>Baſilica</hi> St. <hi>Cuthberts</hi> walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing body in the 309 years after his firſt burial in <hi>Lindisferne</hi> was with great ſolemnity in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhrin'd in the preſence of <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:51010:35"/>Earl of <hi>Northumberland.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Monks</hi> that attended Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> to <hi>Dunholme</hi> was one <hi>Rigulphus,</hi> who was 210. years old: an Hiſtory to be ranked under the ſame place with the wandring <hi>Jew:</hi> a poor Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument to be remembred by, ſith he gives no account to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of his extended age; when number of years is the onely commendation of a man. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers was <hi>Eathred</hi> a <hi>Monk,</hi> who for 6. years before he died could never ſpeak, but in the Church where (as if Religion had then lent him a tongue) no man was more vocal to ſing his part; theſe were the beginnings of the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51010:36"/>Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> where <hi>Ald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winus</hi> the laſt Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and firſt of <hi>Durham,</hi> firſt aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Epiſcopal Chair, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 996. in King <hi>Etheldreds</hi> raign, who whiles Saint <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stane</hi> was baptizing him, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed the Holy Saint with the fruit of his womb, at which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Dunstane</hi> ſwore by God, and by his Mother, that he would prove a lazy fellow; howſoever to prove the lazineſſe of the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Durham,</hi> he gave Saint <hi>Cuthbert, Darlington</hi> with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances, where afterwards <hi>Hugh Puſar</hi> built both a Nunery, and a Church. To theſe poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions <hi>Sunculphus</hi> one of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility added <hi>Bradbury, Mordon,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:51010:36"/>and <hi>Sockburge,</hi> ſo ready was the Devotion in thoſe times, to give all to the Church, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come poor to be made rich in the world to come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aldwinus</hi> dying in the 24th. year after his removing to <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> left only the Weſt-tower of the Church for <hi>Edmundus</hi> to finiſh, who was his ſucceſſor, and choſen Biſhop by a voice out of Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> Tombe, or perchance by a <hi>Monk</hi> (his good freind) who lay hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it: for I do not read that Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> ever drank in his pottage, that (as it is by the Proverbe) <hi>he ſhould ſpeak in his grave.</hi> But without jeſting he was a reverend Prelate, whoſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:51010:37"/>days had the honour which his predeceſſors attaind not to: that now the <hi>Danes</hi> became worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> who had burnt his Church in <hi>Lindisferne:</hi> who now from <hi>Pagans</hi> turned <hi>Christians</hi> in that exceſs of <hi>Devotion,</hi> that <hi>Cumulus</hi> their King came five miles bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot to his Tomb in <hi>Durham,</hi> and gave to the Saint his Church ſo many Towns as would breath a fat <hi>Monk</hi> to repeate them, <hi>Wac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feild, Evenwood, Ingleton, Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton, Staindrop,</hi> and <hi>Rabye,</hi> where the predeceſſors of the <hi>Nevills,</hi> who lye entombed at <hi>Staindrop</hi> Church, built the Caſtle, and held it of the Church of <hi>Durham,</hi> for the annual rent of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51010:37"/>four pounds. The <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Durham</hi> had now ſo fair a Church for their <hi>Saint</hi> to reſt in, that they were aſhamed that ever he had lyen in <hi>Cheſter,</hi> where the Church made of wood ſeemd to remain a Monument of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer poverty, till <hi>Egilrick</hi> the Biſhop took away this eye-ſore, and built Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> a Church of ſtone, which methinks was but a <hi>Poſthumus</hi> dignity to the <hi>Saint,</hi> and like as if a man ſhould ſuſter his gueſt to lie meanly, when he is gone to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for him a better lodging. In digging the foundations of this Church he found ſuch a Maſſe of Coyne, that reſigning his prelateſhip to his Brother at
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51010:38"/>
               <hi>Durham,</hi> he returned to his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey at <hi>Peterburge.</hi> But the King hearing of his Wealth, took oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to pick a quarrel with him, and ſeizing upon his riches im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned him at <hi>Weſtminster.</hi> This King was Duke <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, who approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>York</hi> with an Army ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted the <hi>Monks</hi> at <hi>Durham,</hi> that once more they muſt have Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> upon their back, and fly with him to <hi>Lindisferne,</hi> coming the firſt night to <hi>Jar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> the ſecond to <hi>Bedlington,</hi> the third to <hi>Tugahala,</hi> the fourth to <hi>Holy-Iſland,</hi> whether they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered dryſhod, it being then the time of low Ebb, though the <hi>Monks</hi> compared it to the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51010:38"/>of <hi>Jordan</hi> or the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> as if the water in Homage to their <hi>Saint</hi> had fled back to give them enterance; but the <hi>Monks</hi> ſhortly repaired again to <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> where the Conquerour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning our of <hi>Scotland,</hi> would needs ſee the incorruptible <hi>Saint</hi> ſo magnified. And never were the <hi>Monks</hi> to affraid to have their Impoſture diſcovered; for now they had no leiſure to cheate the ſpectatours with a living <hi>Monk</hi> in ſtead of a dead <hi>Saint:</hi> but made ſo many delays and intreaties to the contrary, that the King with a Fever of Anger was put in ſuch a heat, that haſtening out of the Church, and taking Horſe,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51010:39"/>the <hi>Monks</hi> in their <hi>History</hi> make him never ſtay his courſe, till he had paſſed over the <hi>Teaſe:</hi> King <hi>William</hi> ſhortly after went about to abrogate the royal Charters of the former Kings, whereby Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his <hi>Hally-wark-folke</hi> were freed from tribute. But Saint <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> in a ſleep beate the deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with his paſtoral ſtaffe, that the next morning not able to riſe, he was glad to ſend his Cloak to Saint <hi>Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> his <hi>Sepulcher,</hi> and to aske pardon, before he could receive any eaſe. After this the King had a reverend opinion of Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> and reſtored <hi>Billingham</hi> to the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:51010:39"/>Church, with other villages: and made <hi>Walcherus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi>) Earl of <hi>Northum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berland</hi> Thus the <hi>Monks</hi> had victory over the Conquerour, and brought him under their Religion, who had ſubdued the land with his ſword. All this while the Church of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> was but growing to her <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and height of Glory, which ſhe obtained under the Magnificent Prelate <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Carleife,</hi> who thought the Church that <hi>Aldwin</hi> built too little for ſo great a Saint, and therefore it was pluckt down, and the foundations of a more ample Church laid: <hi>Malcolmus</hi> King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Pryor <hi>Turgot</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:51010:40"/>laying the firſt three ſtones, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 11th. 1093. for which Famous work <hi>Anthony Beak</hi> (one of his ſucceſſors) with a great ſumme of Money got him to be canonized, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled among the <hi>Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Reverend antient Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey (advanced upon the ſhoulder of a Mountainous <hi>Atlas</hi>) is ſo environed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with Hills, that he that hath ſeen the ſcituation of this City, hath ſeen the Map of <hi>Sion;</hi> and may ſave a journy to the <hi>Holy land:</hi> ſhee is girded about with the Renowned River <hi>Weare,</hi> in which (as in a <hi>Christalline</hi>) ſhe migh once have beheld
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:51010:40"/>the beauty, but now the ruines of her Walls. Into this Sumptuous Church was the laſt and great tranſlation of Saint <hi>Cuthbert,</hi> the tradition of whoſe incorruption Pryor <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got</hi> and the reſt of his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren had great diſire to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme with their eyes, and to ſhew him publiquely to the people at the day of his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation. At night therefore the Pryor with ſeven of his Brethren meet at his Tomb, and taking up the ſtone, they found a Cheſt covered with lether, in which they found the Book of the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>list,</hi> which had fallen into the <hi>Sea;</hi> a goblet of pure
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51010:41"/>Gold; and an Ivory combe: laſtly opening the ſecond cheſt, they beheld the fleſh and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of their Saint lying on his right ſide to give place to the reſt of the <hi>Reliques,</hi> which were ſo many that this Coffin ſeemed a <hi>Charnel Houſe;</hi> for beſides his own body, there was the bones of Venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> the head of King <hi>Oſwald,</hi> part alſo of the bones of <hi>Aidanus, Eudfrid,</hi> and <hi>Ethelwaldus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Lindisferne.</hi> All which <hi>Reliques</hi> with due Reverence they placed in another part of the Church, laying only Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> on his back; they placed King <hi>Oſwalds</hi> head between his hands. At the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51010:41"/>day of his tranſlation <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulphus</hi> inſtead of a Funeral preached his Reſurrection Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and publiſhed to the people the incorruption of St. <hi>Cuthbert</hi> his body, which after 418 years was yet flexible, and now might plead preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the grave to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal. Thus in great Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity they inſhrind him beſides the Altar in the preſence of the Abbot of <hi>Sagium,</hi> the Abbot of Saint <hi>Maries</hi> in <hi>York,</hi> and the Abbot of Saint <hi>Germans,</hi> with thoſands of people ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Miracle. This was the place of his reſt, where ſo many Treaſures were daily of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51010:42"/>that the <hi>Monks</hi> needed not to ſtudy <hi>Alchimy</hi> for Gold, having ſuch a <hi>Philoſophers stone</hi> as Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert money to their purſes, who had that repute of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and frequency of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, that in his ſhrine to this day you may ſee the pious di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapidations of Antient devotion: and the very ſtones worn out with kneeling. Here Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> for four hundred years ſlept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſturbance: onely he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd once in a dream to a <hi>Monk</hi> of a Mouſe that troubled his reſt and made her neſt in his Tomb. Hence he lay in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and peace, till <hi>Henry</hi> 8th.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51010:42"/>ſent that Earthquake among Monaſteries and Sepulchres of the Saints which he cauſed to be opened to finde treaſure. Among which (ſaith <hi>Harpe-feild) the Tomb of Saint</hi> Cuth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert <hi>was ſo broken up with that Irreverence, that with the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the blow upon the Coffin, they wounded his Leg; finding the whole body entire ſave the tip of his Noſe that was wanting:</hi> his very grave cloaths were ſo free from corruption, as if they had been kept rather in a <hi>Wardrop</hi> than in a Sepulchre: upon his finger he had a Ring with a <hi>Saphire stone</hi> in it, which for Reverence
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51010:43"/>of the Saint they durſt not take off, but at the Command of Biſhop <hi>Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stal</hi> ſhut up his Tomb as was before. All this might be true, and yet Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> more beholden to the art of his <hi>Monks,</hi> than his own Sanctity, for his incorruption; for it was Ancient amongſt the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> to embalm the bodies of their dead Kings, and with Searecloathes to preſerve their Carkaſſes for many ages from putrefaction, and yet they were thought no Saints ſuch as Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> was: in honour and reverence of whoſe Saint-ſhip till <hi>Edward</hi> the firſts time,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51010:43"/>none preſum'd to be buried in the ſame Church with him, as though unworthy to lye under the ſame roof with ſuch an incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Saint. The moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Monuments therefore are to be ſearched out in the <hi>Chapter Houſe,</hi> where Biſhop <hi>Walcherus</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> lyeth entombed, who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected thoſe ancient buildings called the <hi>Farmary,</hi> for the <hi>Monks</hi> of <hi>Jarroe,</hi> whom with licenſe from <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh he tranſlated to <hi>Durham,</hi> but was miſerably ſlaine in <hi>Gates-Head</hi> Church: whoſe death oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned <hi>Odo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Bayoun</hi> to be ſent hither to take re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge;
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51010:44"/>
               <hi>ſed Exceſſit medicina modum</hi> — For he both depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulated the Church; and rob'd the Countrey of divers Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments. In the ſaid <hi>Charter Houſe</hi> lyeth <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Carleif,</hi> with Pryor <hi>Turgot</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Durham,</hi> and afterwards Biſhop of Saint <hi>Andrewes</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> a polite writer of the Hiſtory of the Church. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to omit others, I ſhall ſpeak a little of Saint <hi>Goodrick,</hi> who becauſe he is one of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Saints, I will ſhew you what he was, out of an old manuſcript writ by one <hi>Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws</hi> of the Priory of <hi>Finchaly.</hi> Saint <hi>Goodrick</hi> in his former
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51010:44"/>years was a Pedlar, and carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his moveable ſhop upon his back from Fair to Fair; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward to make a better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune he ventred into <hi>Flanders, Denmarke,</hi> and <hi>Scotland;</hi> and by the way uſed to viſit the <hi>Holy Iſland,</hi> much delighted to hear the <hi>Monks</hi> tell ſtories of their Saint <hi>Cuthbert:</hi> which ſo deeply affected him, that he would needs in heat of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion undertake a Pilgrimage to the <hi>Holy Iſland:</hi> and again after his return to <hi>England</hi> by the advice of Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> he repaired to his <hi>Holy Sepulchre,</hi> and alſo waſhing his feet in <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan,</hi> there left his ſhoos, vowing to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51010:45"/>go barefot all his life after. At his ſecond return he was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed by Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> in his ſleep to build him an Anchoridge at <hi>Fenchallie</hi> near <hi>Durham,</hi> where he lived in that heat of Devotion, that he uſed to ſtand praying up to the neck in the river that run by his Cell, which holy cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſo angred the Divel, that once he ſtole away his Cloaths, as they lay on the Bank: but <hi>Goodrick</hi> ſeeing him, brought him back with an <hi>Ave Mary,</hi> and forceing the Devil to be juſt againſt his will made him reſtore them: which were ſo courſe, as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51010:45"/>(I think) he that ſtole them, would ſcarce have worn them: for his Jerkin was of Iron, of which he wore three ſuits in the time of his <hi>Hermitage:</hi> a ſtrange Coate whoſe ſtuffe had the Iron-monger for the Draper, and a Smith for the Tailor; neither was his lodging much unſuitable to his Cloathes, who had the ground for his bed, and a ſtone for his pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. His tutelary Angel oft played the Sexton, and rang his bell to awake him to his Nocturnes; who for want of beades uſed with pebble ſtones to number his prayers; his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51010:46"/>dyet was as coarſe as his coat; and as his ſhirts were made of ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, ſo half the Meal that made him Bread was aſhes. The Divel uſed to act Proteus before him, and with his ſhapes rather made him ſport, than affrighted him; only as Saint <hi>Goodrick</hi> ſate by the fire, the Divel came behind him, and gave him ſuch a box of the eare, that he had fell'd him down, if he had not recovered himſelf with the ſign of the Croſſe. Thus after he had acted a Legend of miracles, he ended his ſceane and his life <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1170. little deſerving this Honour to be beſtowed by <hi>Hugh Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:51010:46"/>the Biſhop on his Cell, who had told him, that he ſhould be ſeven years blind before his death: ſo that the Biſhop believing the <hi>Holy Hermit,</hi> and deferring his repentance (which <hi>Goodrick</hi> meant of the eyes of his underſtanding) died unprovided for death: But if good deeds be ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, then died he not in debt for his ſins, who repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red many of the Epiſcopal mannors, builded <hi>Darlington</hi> Church, founded the Hoſpital at <hi>Allerton,</hi> the famous <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burne</hi> Hoſpital near <hi>Durham;</hi> built <hi>Elvet Bridge</hi> with the Chappells upon it; who bought
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51010:47"/>of <hi>King Richard</hi> the firſt the Earldome of <hi>Sadbury</hi> for his ſucceſſours; and laſt of all built that beautifull work the <hi>Gallile</hi> or our <hi>Ladies Chappel,</hi> now called the <hi>Conſistory,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he tranſlated Saint <hi>Bedes</hi> bones, which lye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr'd under a ſtone of Marble; from this place (I conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) the great Bell in <hi>Alby</hi> hath its name, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance is the ſame, which in an Old Manuſcript I find to be drawn from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Durham</hi> by twenty two <hi>Oxen:</hi> under the Conſiſtory Table lyeth intombed Cardinal <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham,</hi> and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:51010:47"/>Lord Chancellour of <hi>England,</hi> who built the <hi>Muſick</hi> and <hi>Grammar Schools.</hi> In the Quire lyeth Biſhop <hi>Beaumount</hi> under a ſpacious Marble inlaid with braſſe, beſides whom Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Anthony Beake</hi> Patriark of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who had the principality of the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> was inſhrin'd in the <hi>Altar.</hi> He built (ſaith <hi>Leland</hi>) the Mannor of <hi>Aukland,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired <hi>Barnard,</hi> and <hi>Anwick</hi> Caſtle, and made <hi>Chester</hi> a Collegiate Church. No Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Monuments of Women are to be ſeen here; for till of late no female was to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> Churches;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:51010:48"/>ſince once on a time (as he was preaching) the Divel came to his Sermon in the ſhape of a moſt beautifull Woman: who ſo drew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the attention of the auditors by gazing upon her, that Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Holy-water</hi> at her found that ſhe was a Divel. But as for Saint <hi>Cuthbert</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, I obſerve his nature did not much loath the company of his holy ſift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: for <hi>Hilda, Alfreda, Verca, Elba,</hi> and other Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bateſſes were of his inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate acquaintance: and if he had ſo diſtaſted that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:51010:48"/>ſex, he had not built a Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at <hi>Carile.</hi> But to return, in the Quire at the North ſide lieth Biſhop <hi>Skirlaw,</hi> who built the Steeple at <hi>Holmes Church;</hi> and a great part of the <hi>Lanthorne</hi> of <hi>York-minster:</hi> who beſtowed moreover two hundred pound on building the diſtributory at <hi>Durham:</hi> which is the <hi>Checker</hi> over the Abby gates. The reliques of this Abbey were as many as there are Saints in the Popes <hi>Almanack;</hi> for hence was Saint <hi>Giles</hi> to fetch his tooth at the Reſurrection, another Saint his leg, another his hipbone, another his skull,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:51010:49"/>another his knuckle bone: and if you would know what price reliques were at in thoſe dayes, aske <hi>Malmesbury</hi> what <hi>Egelmothus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury</hi> gave as he came from <hi>Rome</hi> for Saint <hi>Augustines</hi> arme which he brought from <hi>Paria,</hi> and he will tell you, that it coſt him a hundred talents of Silver, and one of gold, by which bargain he hath made himſelf (by Record) a fool to poſterity, and thoſe that have read that in <hi>Plinie, Mala emptio ſemper ingrata, eo quod maxime domino exprobrare ſtultiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am videtur.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:51010:49"/>
            <p> But of all reliques to make merry with, this is one; <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fride</hi> a <hi>Monk</hi> had <hi>got one</hi> of Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> Hairs, which laid upon the Coals, would be red-hot, and return again to its former colour: thus not ſo: much as a Hair of Saint <hi>Cuthberts</hi> could eſcape without a miracle. Among other mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents of this Abbey the braſen deske is not the leaſt, which was the joynt guilt of a reverend Prebend of this Church, and his Son who ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Globe; and the Eagle to that ſumptuous baſis and columne, which was the twelfth
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:51010:50"/>part of a great Candleſtick, found hid in the vault of the Church; who both lye buried under two Marble ſtones, inlaid with Braſſe, as you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in at the Quire door on your left hand. The ſubter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raneous paſſages under this Church, as in other Abbeys, are many: but what end theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions ſhould have in the makers intent, whether to conceal their treaſures in time of invaſion, or for worſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes I cannot determine. By thoſe Cavernes, the Abbey and the Caſtle certainly ſhaked hands together under ground. The Caſtle was built by <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:51010:50"/>the Conquerour for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the City, the Iron gate whereof was ſet up by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, <hi>Tonſtal,</hi> who alſo built the <hi>Tolbooth.</hi> The Tower (in which <hi>Philip Potier</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> had Licenſe by <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt to ſet up a Minthouſe, and coyne Money) was repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Richad Fox,</hi> and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. <hi>Winton</hi> the Honourable founder of <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> whereof at this time I am a member. In the Chappel of which Colledge were two Altars, the one cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Ara Trinitatis,</hi> the other, <hi>Ara Sancti Cuthberti.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:51010:51"/>
            <p> To conclude, the whole Caſtle was repaired, and beautifully a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned, and enlightned with Windows by the Reverend Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop now Incumbent, under whom the Church of <hi>Durham</hi> ſeemes to renew her age, and take a new leaſe of her Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which for the internal beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her high Altar, Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral muſick, ſacred laver, and other ornaments may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge her ſiſter. Churches for Priority.</p>
            <p>Thus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,or like one that at once ſalutes a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, I have taken a confuſed ſurvey of the Monuments of this
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:51010:51"/>Church, with that diſtracted method and brevity, that I have rather ſeemed to take an Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of her Antiquities, than to have compiled an Hiſtory. As it is I offer it upon one of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, which the <hi>Romans</hi> uſed to erect with this inſcription, <hi>Diis Patrus.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
